Hi everyone, our
lecture today is in
Arterial Blood
Pressure Regulation.
For this lecture we have
four learning objectives,
so we will discuss the
short-term and the long-term
blood pressure regulation,
how these two processes
maintain the normal levels
of arterial blood pressure.
So for the short-term blood
pressure regulation, we
will discuss about
baroreceptors, chemoreceptors,
atrial reflex,
and the central nervous
system ischemic response.
And for the long
-term blood pressure
regulation, we
will discuss about
the role of the renin
-angiotensin system
in the kidneys and
in the vasculature.
Also, we will discuss
a little bit about the
hypovolemic shock, how
this process can be
regulated by arterial
blood pressure,
and we will discuss
some clinical
applications of blood
pressure regulation.
So here is some review
of the definitions
that we already saw in
our previous lectures.
So we need to just
review that to explain
the mechanism of blood
pressure regulation.
So stroke volume is
the amount of the
blood pump by the
heart in each beat.
Cardiac output is the volume
of blood that the heart
pumps through the circulation
per minute. So, cardiac
output is stroke volume
multiplied by heart rate.
And the average number
that we consider normal
is around 5 liters per
minute for cardiac output.
So, we will also need
to review this concept
about total peripheral
resistance. So, when
you see the term systemic
vascular resistance,
both means the same.
So, total peripheral
resistance is equal to mean
arterial pressure divided
by cardiac output.
And the mean arterial
pressure is the aberration
arterial pressure through
one cardiac cycle.
So to have an ideal tissue
perfusion, we should have
a mean arterial pressure
higher than 60 millimeters
of mercury. If for some
reason this mean arterial
pressure drop, we will
have a deficit in the
tissue perfusion and this
is an emergency situation.
So here are the two
equations that we
use to calculate mean
arterial pressure.
Cardiac output
multiplied by total
peripheral resistance and
also mean arterial pressure
is equal two times the
diastolic plus the
systolic divided by three.
So cardiac output
is crucial for
the determination
of blood pressure.
So the two parameters
that will define cardiac
output is stroke
volume and heart rate.
So let's start with heart rate.
Heart rate can be controlled
by the nervous system,
sympathetic and
parasympathetic. So if we have
activation of the sympathetic,
we will have one
increase in heart rate.
For example, when we
are doing some physical
activity, we activate
our sympathetic
and that will increase
the heart rate and
will result in increase
of cardiac output.
If we have activation
of the parasympathetic,
they will cause a decrease
in the heart rate.
So another factor
that will determine
cardiac output is
the stroke volume.
So if we have one increase in
the central venous pressure,
that will lead to increase
in the preload, that
preload and end of the
diastolic volume means
the same thing, that will
increase stroke volume.
Another factor that can
change stroke volume is
contractility. If we have an
increase of contractility,
that will cause one
increase in stroke volume.
And if we have one
increase in the afterload,
that will cause a decrease
in the stroke volume.
So the takeaway of this
slide is that we need to
remember that every
time we have a change in
cardiac output that can
happen for two reasons or
we have a change in
heart rate or changing in
stroke volume or perhaps
perhaps we have change
in both blood pressure
is a hydraulic equation.
So blood pressure is
equal cardiac output
multiplied by total
peripheral resistance.
If I have an increase
in cardiac output,
I will have an increase
in blood pressure.
If we have an increase in
total peripheral resistance,
we also will have an
increase in blood pressure.
And if we have a decrease
in cardiac output
and decrease in the total
peripheral resistance,
we will have a decrease
in blood pressure.
So blood pressure
regulation is basically
divided in two
regulations. We have
the short term and we
have the long term.
So short term is when
we need to quickly
regulate the blood pressure
and the long term is
when since we born
until we become a senior
in the long of your life
we need to control our
blood pressure so this we
call the long term and the
short term is when we
have some specific events
that for some reason I have
a drop in my blood pressure
and I need to increase
very quick, that will
happen via the short-term
blood pressure regulation.
I take credit here, this
part for this cat is from
one of my previous students,
Maricelli, that she was a
scholar in the lab and she
used her cat to explain
the mechanism of short-term
blood pressure regulation.
So again, we have these
two physiologic systems
primarily responsible for
blood pressure management,
the short-term and the long
-term. In the short-term,
we have the bottle receptors
and also the chemio
receptors. So these receptors
will be activated in
a short term in order to
regulate blood pressure.
In the other side, the
long-term blood pressure is
basically regulated by the
Renin-Agiotensin system.
So let's take a
look first the short
-term. What do we have
in the short-term?
We have these battle
receptors, so battle receptors
are receptors that can
sense changes in blood
pressure and also we
have the chemoreceptors.
Both receptors are
located in the aortic
arch and also here
in the carotid sinus.
So these receptors
they can sense when
we have a change in
the blood pressure.
So this information
via afferent here in
blue will send the message
if the blood pressure
is too high or too
low to the medulla
via these two nerves
number nine number ten
glossopharyngeal in
the vagus and then as a
response via efferent here
in green they will activate
or sympathetic or
parasympathetic that will
have effect in the blood
vessels and in the heart.
The long-term blood pressure
regulation is a
systemic regulation.
So,
in a situation that we
have a drop in blood
pressure, the blood
pressure is really low,
that will activate our
kidneys to produce renin.
Renin is an enzyme
that can convert
angiotensinogen
in angiotensin-1.
So angiotensinogen is this
peptide produced by the liver.
It's always circulating
in the circulation, in
the bloodstream. But in
the presence of renin,
angiotensin inogen is cleaved
and form angiotensin 1.
Angiotensin 1 has no effect.
Angiotensin 1 need be
converted in angiotensin 2.
And angiotensin 2 is the
most potent vasoconstrictor
that we have in
your body. So, this
conversion happens via
ACE, is the enzyme that's
produced by several
tissues, but the main
source is the endothelial
cells from the lungs.
So, once we have high levels of
angiotensin II in
our circulation,
angiotensin II will bind
to a specific receptor
we call angiotensin
type 1 receptor, and
we can find this
receptor in the majority
of tissues in your body,
in the vasculature,
in the kidney, in
adrenal cortex,
in several tissues.
But the main effect of
the angiotensin II is
they will bind to its
receptor in the vascular
smooth muscle cells and
cause vasoconstriction.
Angiotensin II also activates
the sympathetic activate
that also will contribute
to vasoconstriction.
They will activate the
pituitary gland to release
ADH. They will activate
the adrenal cortex that
will produce aldosterone
and aldosterone will
retain sodium and also
angiotensin 2 can act in
the kidney causing water
and sodium reabsorption.
All together, they will
increase blood pressure.
So you can see how complex
is the renegotiating system.
They can act in different
tissues and all the
effects will lead to an
increase in the blood pressure.
So today one of the drugs
of choice to decrease
blood pressure is use
drugs that can inhibit
the renin-angiotensin
system. We have drugs
that, for example, will
inhibit the ACE enzyme,
angiotensin-convert enzyme.
So these are the ACE
inhibitors. So they will
inhibit the conversion
of angiotensin 1 to
angiotensin 2. So you
have less levels of this
potent vasoconstrictor.
Another drug is the ARB,
are the drugs that will
block the angiotensin
receptor. So we have a drug
that will act here and the
ones that will act
blocking, they impede that
angiotensin to bind to the
angiotensin type 1 receptor.
So, again, based on all
this information, today
exist several drugs that
interfere in the system
in order to decrease
blood pressure. So, those
drugs are highly used
to control hypertension.
So, short-term blood
pressure regulation,
they will regulate
the diameter of the
vessel, heart rate
and contractility.
This regulation happens in
seconds to minutes. It's
very quick and occurs through
the neural pathway. So
what is the key players? We
have the bottom receptors,
we have the chemoreceptors,
we have the central
nervous system ischemic
response and atrial reflex.
All of them play a role
in the short-term blood
pressure regulation.
So again, here we have
the short-term blood
pressure regulation. Remember
that these receptors,
the Let's imagine that
they can sense that
the blood pressure
is pretty high. They
will send this information
to the medulla,
saying the blood
pressure is pretty high.
And as a response
via efferent, they
will activate the
parasympathetic
to try to slow down heart
rate and vasodilate, cause
vasodilation. together they
will drop blood pressure.
Now let's think in
another situation. If
you have a low blood
pressure, these receptors
will sense and will
tell to your brain,
listen, the blood
pressure is pretty low.
What we should do?
Well, let's activate the
sympathetic and the
sympathetic will cause
vasoconstriction,
increase heart rate, and
together they will
increase blood pressure.
So here is just the
summary of this figure.
What you need to
remember is where those
baroreceptors and the
chemoreceptors are located.
The afferent and
efferent pathway.
and where they act. So
in this figure we can
see that the efferent
via sympathetic and
parasympathetic, they
can act in the heart,
in the blood vessel,
but also in the
adrenal medulla. That's
not showing here.
So who never faces
this kind of situation
when you realize you
are late to go to
school and you jump
quickly from your bed.
So again this is
Marichelle's cat.
So what's happened? You
are sleeping or your
alarms start ringing and
you jump from the bed.
You feel like your
heart is going
to jump from your mouth, right?
You have palpitation
and then you stabilize.
So, if you are laid down
and you stand too quick,
there is a drop in the blood
pressure that will be sensed
by the body receptors.
So the body receptors
will send this information
to your brain, say the
blood pressure is low.
So from the medulla,
the efferent reflex
will increase the
sympathetic activity
and as a result,
they will cause
increase of heart rate,
increase of stroke volume, and
then increase of
blood pressure.
So it's very common when
someone is laid down and wake
up very fast, they have
palpitations and dizziness,
right? Because you need
to wake up very slowly,
sit in your bed first,
and then you stand up.
If you do this too quickly,
you will activate your
bioreceptor reflex and
that's why you feel this
palpitation and dizziness
because the amount of
blood from this position
to your brain will drop.
So this is the
bioreceptor reflex.
So
these receptors that is in
the sinus of carotid and
the aortic arch, they
will sense if the blood
pressure is drop they will
send this information for
your medulla via afferent
and then the efferent
you will have activation of
your sympathetic activity
that will cause
vasoconstriction so increase of
systemic vascular
resistance and will increase
cardiac output and that will
increase blood pressure.
The specific region in
the in the medulla that
regulate the blood pressure
is the NTS nucleus tractus
solitarius. This is the
specific region that
control blood pressure. So
there is some researchers,
scientists, that they
study the blood pressure
regulation in the brain
because we know the brain
plays a key role in
regulating blood pressure.
So this is the summary of
the bottle receptor reflex.
So here is a situation where
we have one increase of
blood pressure and the bottle
receptor will sense that.
So as a response,
decrease sympathetic
activation and increase
the parasympathetic.
So in the end, you have
a decrease in heart rate,
decrease cardiac output,
decrease peripheral
resistance, and all together
they will cause decrease
in blood pressure.
And in another situation,
when you're having
decrease of blood
pressure, also this
will be sensed by
the baroreceptors,
so they will stimulate
the sympathetic and shut
down the parasympathetic
in order to have increase
of heart rate,
vasoconstriction, increase of
peripheral resistance,
increase of cardiac output
because we have increase
of heart rate, and
together they will cause
increase in blood pressure.
So, how we can activate
our baroreceptor
reflex without
waking up very fast?
Well, you can use the
valsalva maneuver.
So the valsalva maneuver
is this forceful exhalation
against the closed airway.
So you close your mouth,
your nose, and what you
are going to do, you are
going to cause one increase
in intrathoracic pressure.
So in this way, you trick
your baroreceptor. your
battle receptor when you do
the valsalva maneuver they
will sense that the blood
pressure is going up so as
a response you will the
battle receptor will sense
will send this information
to the medulla saying oh the
the blood pressure it seems
to be high so what the
efferent part will do.
They will activate the
parasympathetic and they will
shut down the sympathetic and
as a response we will have
a decrease in heart rate.
So this is a maneuver
that you can also use when
you have a case of a
supraventricular tachycardia.
Someone come to the ER with
tachycardia, if you ask
the patient to proceed
doing the Valsalva maneuver,
they will be able to decrease
their heart rate, basic
because they are activating
the baroreceptor reflex.
So, the
way that we have
to activate the
baroreceptors is by
doing carotid massage.
So, this is also a,
let's say, a manipulation
that you can see a
lot in ER when you
have a patient with
tachycardia and you need
to decrease the heart
rate pretty quick,
you do a massage here in
the carotid, exactly where
we could find the bowel
receptors. When you do this
massage, you trick your
bowel receptors. You make
your bowel receptors feel
that the blood pressure is
going up, but it's not.
You are doing the massage.
So the viral receptor will
send this message to the
central nervous system,
specifically in the NTS area.
And as a response,
the efferent will increase
the parasympathetic activity.
And that will cause
a drop of heart rate.
I include here in
this slide, it's
something astral but
it's just for you read
when you start studying
for your boards.
There is something that
we call carotid sinus
hypersensitivity
syndrome is when you can,
let's say, accidentally
or hyper-stimulated
the baroreceptor. So that
you can find in older
patients, more in male,
not much in female,
patients that have
atherosclerotic
disease or they have
prior neck surgery
or neck irradiation
to treat cancer.
So their baroreceptor
system is hypersensitive,
so all the time they
sense that there
is alteration in
blood pressure.
So for the board exam
questions. You will
see things like elderly
male patients
presenting with syncope
episodes occurring while
trying to put their
shirt or when they are
shaving or they are
brushing their hair because
they can accidentally
hyper-stimulate the
viral receptors. So
here's the summary of
the short-term blood
pressure regulation by
the bottle receptors. So
you will see when you
have increase of blood
pressure, what is the effect
of the bottle receptor
reflex, and when you
have decrease of blood
pressure, how the bottle
receptor reflex acts.
So here we finalize the
receptor reflex. The next one
that we are going to discuss
is the chymio receptors.
The chymio receptors similar
to the body receptors,
they are also located
here in the aortic arch
and also in the carotid.
Those receptors are very
sensitive to detect changes
in oxygen, CO2 and pH.
So when they sense that
the levels, for example,
of oxygen is decreasing
the blood and there
is an increase of CO2
and a decrease in pH,
they will send this
information using the same
nerves utilized by the
receptors, the nerve 9 and 10,
send this information to the
medulla and as a response
we will have one increase
in sympathetic activity
and that will lead to
increase of blood pressure.
So here we have the two
receptors that play a role
in the short-term regulation
of blood pressure,
the battle receptors here
and the chemoreceptors.
So the chemoreceptors
they can sense a
decrease in the pH and
oxygen and also when
we have an increase
of CO2 that will
cause one increase in
sympathetic activity.
In the body receptors
they can sense one
increase in blood pressure
and that's what they
are going to cause or
they can also sense
a decrease in blood
pressure and that are
the consequences of the
baroreceptor reflex.
So the next topic that
we are going to discuss
is the central nervous
system ischemic reflex.
It's a reflex that also
plays a role in the
short-term regulation
of blood pressure.
Let's say for any
reason you have a
severe drop in the
cerebral blood flow.
There is no much blood
coming to your brain,
or because of bleeding,
some accident.
So that will cause ischemia.
During ischemia, we have
an accumulation of CO2.
This accumulation of CO2
will cause excitation
of neurons of the vasomotor
center in the brain.
And as a response, we will have
this powerful vasoconstriction
that will cause an
increase in blood pressure.
So every time we
have a decrease of
blood flow in the
brain, one of the
symptoms that we will
see in the patient is an
increase in blood pressure
because of this reflex.
And another reflex that
happens and also controls
blood pressure regulation
in a short term
is a reflex that we
call cushion reflex.
In some test book you can
also find cushion reflex
as a cushion
response, is a type of
central nervous system
ischemic response,
is a medical emergency,
is a life-threatening.
So what is the possible
causes of cushion reflex?
If you have any head injury,
some intracranial bleeding,
some tumors is
growing in the brain,
inflammation in the
central nervous system,
if you have excess of CSF
overproduction or the mechanism
that the drain the CSF is
not working well and if
have some metabolic variations
for example hyponatremia
low levels of sodium so all
these situations can cause
one increase in intracranial
pressure if you have
increase of pressure in the
brain that will constrict the
arteriolus and that will
cause a decrease in cerebral
blood flow that's is very
similar here to this reflex
when we also have a decrease
in cerebral blood flow.
So that will cause
ischemia. In ischemia we
know we have high levels
of CO2 and low pH,
so become very acid.
And as a response you
have activation of the
sympathetics, that will
increase blood pressure.
However, when we, when you
increase blood pressure,
that will be sensed by
the viral receptors.
And what the viral receptors
will do, will send this
information to the brain
and say, you know now, so in
the beginning we have this
decrease in cerebral blood
flow, but now we have an
increase of blood pressure.
So, this information goes
to the central nervous
system and the bowel
receptors will activate the
parasympathetic and that
will decrease heart rate.
So, the Cushing
reflex triide is
characterized by hypertension,
then low heart rate and
respiratory depression.
So the last system
that we will discuss
that play a role in
the short-term blood
pressure regulation is
the atrial reflex that
is also called as a
main bridget reflex.
This is a physiological
reflex that is mediate by the
stretch receptors located
in the atria of the heart.
So how this reflex is
activated. Let's say you
have an increase in the
venous return to the
heart, oops, here,
that will cause a
distension of these
receptors and as a result
you will have an
increase in heart rate.
So if we see here this
schematic figure, if you have
increase of blood volume,
because you will have
increase of venous return
to the heart that will cause
one activation of these
receptors located in the
atrium, they sense this
amount of blood and as a
result they will send this
information to the brain and
the brain will activate
the sympathetic and will
inhibit the parasympathetic.
So as a result you have
increase of heart rate.
So, during this mechanism,
your body reflex will
say to remove this excess
of blood in the heart,
let's increase heart rate.
And this is not much part of
the blood pressure regulation
that I mentioned in the
beginning, but I would
like to mention about the
AMP, that is a peptide that
you will see a lot during
the cardiovascular lectures.
So when you also stretch
the atrium, let's say
for increase of venous
return, you can activate
a specific cardiomyocytes
in the atrium that will
produce this AMP, atrial
natriuretic peptides.
So these peptides, they
will activate the cyclic GMP
mechanism and these peptides,
they cause vasodilation.
So when they cause
vasodilation, we will
have a drop in total
peripheral resistance
and that will drop
blood pressure.
This peptide also has
some effect in the kidney,
so they cause a decrease
of sodium reabsorption,
they dilate the
efferent arteriolus,
so all together they will
cause a drop in blood
pressure. They will cause
diuresis and this is
important for you to remember
that this peptide they
can be released in the
bloodstream when we have a
atrial stretch and this
peptide is a vasodilator and
also has important
actions in the kidney and
together all these effects
will drop blood pressure.
So, here we have some
review questions.
So when you are
studying, it is good to
remember where the bowel
receptors are located.
Which cranial
nerves are involved
in the bowel receptor reflex?
So 9 and 10.
Which part of the medulla
receives the afferent
signals involved in the
baroreceptor reflex? The NTS.
Briefly describe
baroreceptor reflex in the
case that we have
hypotension. So this is one
case that we mentioned
before when you are sleeping
or laid down and you
stand up very quick.
And also explain how increase
of blood pressure and
decrease in heart rate
occurs in the cushion reflex.
So I have all the answers
for these questions here.
So this is a review of
the first part of our
lecture, so if you have
any questions please
contact me later, but
it's very straightforward.
Here we have one
pretext question.
I will give you
one minute to read.
So this question is about
what happens if I
cut the vagus nerve.
There is some surgeries
that do vagotomy for many
reasons and how that
would affect the blood
pressure regulation or the
bottle receptor reflex.
So here is the answer.
So if you go back in the in
the slides I have showing
the bottle receptor, you
can see exactly which
one is connected with the
vagus, the butto-receptors
in the aortic arch or the
butto-receptors in the
carotid. So, this is
something is anatomic
acknowledgement that is very
important for you to know.
So, if you have some
damage or cut of
the vagus nerve,
that would remove the
parasympathetic
stimulation to the heart.
Therefore, with the unopposed
sympathetic stimulation
in the heart, the heart
rate would increase.
So until here we just
discussed about the short
-term regulation of blood
pressure. Now we will
discuss the long-term
blood pressure regulation.
So, the long-term blood
pressure regulation is really,
really important since
the day we're born and
until we get old. Because
if you don't have regulation
of your blood pressure,
that will cause several
issues. For example, you
can develop stroke, vision
problems, heart attack,
kidney disease, heart failure,
sexual dysfunction.
So having a good control of
your blood pressure is crucial.
And the system that mainly
control long-term blood
pressure regulation is the
Renin-Ajotin-Sin system.
So this type of regulation they
take hours, day, month, years.
So this is a hormonal system
that in the end we have
this peptide that we call
angiotensin 2. This is the
most potent vasoconstrictor
that we have in your body.
So when you have activation
of this system, you will
have all these effects that
we already mentioned. So
you will have vasoconstriction,
sympathetic activation,
high levels of ADH, high
levels of aldosterone,
you will affect negatively
your kidney function,
so you have water and
sodium reabsorption.
And all these effects
caused by angiotensin
2 will lead to increasing
blood pressure.
So kidney,
the effect of angiotensin
2 in the kidney and in
the vascular smooth
muscle that will cause
vasoconstriction is one of
the main effects of the renal
angiotensin system that
will lead to increase of
blood pressure and then
development of hypertension.
So let's see the renal
blood pressure regulation
that involves the just
agglomerular apparatus. So
here, I will be very, I
will simplify because you
will have these in details
in renal physiology.
But just to focus on
how this system plays a
role in control of blood
pressure, I make this
relatively simple
schematic figure to try and
understand how this
system plays a role in
the regulation of blood
pressure. So, let's say
in a situation that
you have hypoperfusion,
low blood flow
coming to the kidney,
mainly because the
blood pressure drops.
So you have a decrease in
renal perfusion pressure.
Let's imagine someone with,
I don't know, let's
say it's a very hot
day, someone start
to have dehydration
and the blood pressure
starts to drop.
That can lead to a decrease in
the renal perfusion pressure.
And when you also, there
is situation that you
can have hyponatremia
drop in sodium chloride,
you are dehydrating, and
that can be sensed by your
kidney, but in a specific
part of the kidney.
So here we make a
zoom and you can
see the just
glomerular apparatus.
It's all this part. They
contain the macula densa,
the just a glomerular or
granular cells in the dark
purple and the mesangial
cells in the light purple.
Also you have here the afferent
arteriola and the
efferent arteriola.
Inside of the afferent
arteriola we have a bottle
receptors. So if we have a
drop in the renal perfusion,
the viral receptor
here, they will sense.
They will sense two
things. They can
sense that the blood
pressure is low and
then the macula
densa is here in this
light green. They
can sense that
there is low levels of sodium.
So, what they are
going to do, they will
activate the just
agglomerular or granular
cells, these black purple
cells, and these cells
are the ones that will
release the renin.
So, you will have an
increase of renin release,
and we know that renin
is this enzyme that
will convert angiotensinogen
and angiotensin 1.
and the ACE enzyme will convert
angiotensin-1 and
angiotensin-2.
So, if I have increase
of angiotensin-2,
I will have
vasoconstriction and all the
consequences I showed
in the previous slides,
increase aldosterone, cause
vasoconstriction, and all
these will lead to increase
of blood pressure. So
here I put some summary.
So when you have
release of renin from
those granular cells,
they will activate the
renin-angiotensin system,
will cause
vasoconstriction, they will
also increase sodium
and water reabsorption,
and that will cause
increase in blood pressure.
So when we measure
blood pressure in
the patient, this is
an indirect method.
We do the same in the
lab. We can measure
blood pressure in
rodents, for example, and
we measure in the tail
of the rats or mice.
This technique is
the same technique
used in human and is
an indirect method.
So they give an estimation how
is the real blood pressure.
The best way to
measure blood pressure
is a direct method,
when you can put
the catheter directly
in the artery.
So, in the research lab,
we are able to do that. So,
we implant a pressure catheter
in the carotid, and in
this way, we can measure
continuous blood pressure.
So here is one preliminary
data from our lab,
just showing, comparing
normal and obese mice.
So we can record blood
pressure for 24, 48 hours,
and we can exactly see when
blood pressure is higher.
In this case, it is
in the dark cycle.
And this is very important
because when the patients
go to the clinic or to
the hospital they do one
measurement and maybe
the time they measure was
normal or the time they
measure was high that doesn't
represent the whole uh
the whole idea how is the
blood pressure of this
patient just taking one
measurement so the ideal is
take at least 24, 48 hours.
Maybe the blood
pressure is higher in
the morning, maybe
it's in the night.
And another thing that we need
to take into consideration
is when you do this
indirect method that is just
one measurement, we have
several factors that play
a role. One of them is the
white coat syndrome. It's
just the fact that the
patient sees someone in the
white coat, They get so
stressed and nervous that when
they measure their blood
pressure, it will be high.
What doesn't actually mean that
the patient has hypertension,
right? And more recently,
I will not have time to
discuss that, but we know today
that there is a difference
in blood pressure
regulation in men and women.
So the mechanism
that regulates blood
pressure in women is
different from men.
However,
all the treatments we
have nowadays, the anti
-hypertensive treatments,
they are the same for
men and women. And
most of them have been
developed in pre-clinical
research using males.
So this is something that
has been more take attention
of the scientists and
the medical community
that in a couple of years
we will treat hypertension
maybe in a different way
if it's a man or a woman.
So we need to take in
consideration the
sex difference.
So, here we have
the summary of the
activation of the renal
angiotensin system.
This is just, once
again, the summary.
And the takeaway about
this system is that
every time we have
increase of angiotensin II,
it's a vasoconstrictor,
very potent. They will
cause effect in many
tissues, and all the
effects will lead to
increase of blood pressure.
Angiotensin too,
something that I didn't
mention before, can also
increase the thirst.
So the patient or the
person will drink more.
And if you have more volume,
you can increase
stroke volume, and that
can lead to increase
of cardiac output.
and you have increase
of blood pressure.
So angiotensin-2 is
this potent peptide
that causes vasoconstriction
and they bind in
a specific receptor
called AT1 receptor.
So we know that when
angiotensin-2 binds to this
receptor they will cause
vasoconstriction but
also there is another
other effects, several
effects. And most of these
effects are negative.
So, for example, they
can cause hypertrophy
of smooth muscle cells,
fibrosis, inflammation,
migration, calcification,
contraction. All these will
cause a vascular remodeling.
So, angiotensin II
in high levels can be
very detrimental for
the vascular system.
Also angiotensin 2 can
increase the oxidative stress
and we know oxidative
stress is detrimental for
the vascular function. So
this is just for you keep
in mind that angiotensin
2 not only cause
vasoconstriction but also have
another other effects that
cause vascular damage,
vascular dysfunction that
will contribute also for
increase of blood pressure.
So the clinical relevance. So
hypertension is
a silence killer.
People will discover that
they have high blood pressure
when they have the symptoms
and most of the time
is late. Or I have a
headache or I start bleeding,
and then they will detect
that the blood pressure is
pretty high. Some patient
doesn't have any symptoms.
So what is the risk factors?
I have a list all of them here,
and most of them we can avoid.
Obesity,
development of type 2 diabetes,
overconsumption of
diet high in sodium,
So, all fast food,
some drinks that we
consume is really high
in salt, like sodas,
excess of alcohol, smoking,
sedentarism. All these
really contributes to the
development of hypertension.
So, 90% of the cases
of hypertension
we call primary hypertension.
is we don't know
the exact cause.
And the secondary hypertension
corresponds for
10% of the case.
Those ones are the ones
that have a specific
problem, for example,
in the kidneys.
But unfortunately,
the majority of the
hypertension cases, we
don't know how they start.
So here I put a table.
again this is you will have
these lectures but just
to know that we have a
guidelines that is from
American Heart Association and
based on the values you
will determine if the
person had elevated blood
pressure or they already
have hypertension so those
guidelines you always need
to be up to the date
because they always reveal.
And some of the last
things I have heard is
that maybe in the
future we will have
separate guidelines for
men and for women to
determine if they have
hypertension or not.
And lastly, I will
talk about shock.
So, shock is a life-threatening
circulatory disorder.
is high mortality rate
every time you have a
shock is a panic is when
you have a drop in the blood
pressure if you don't have
an ideal blood pressure
so high blood pressure
is danger but low blood
pressure as is danger as
well so if you don't have a
good blood pressure, it's
too low, the blood will
not reach many tissues,
brain, kidney, gut, and if
you don't have enough blood
coming to the tissues,
you will have organ damage.
So let's say in the case
of hypovolemic So, from
the bottom to the top, you
have the types of shock,
so hypovolemic,
cardiogenic, when you have
a heart failure, and
you have the septic and
anaphylactic shock.
That's very important.
All this shock will
lead to low tissue
perfusion due to drop
in blood pressure.
So, the treatment, you
need to give volume,
you need to increase
blood pressure to
start to reperfuse the
tissues with blood.
So, let's say you have
some accident, you
have a huge bleeding,
you lose blood volume,
that will cause a
drop in cardiac output
because you decrease
stroke volume. That will
cause a decrease in
blood pressure and shock.
If your heart is weak,
it's not pumping well,
you will have a drop in
cardiac output because
probably your heart
rate will start to drop.
That also will cause a
drop in blood pressure.
How about the septic
and anaphylactic shock?
In those kind of shock
you have a release
of, for example, histamine or
bradykinine that cause
a huge vasodilation.
And if you have a huge
vasodilation, you will
decrease the total
peripheral resistance.
And if you have a decrease
in total peripheral
resistance, you have a
decrease in blood pressure.
So shock is pretty much
that. It's when you have
hypoperfusion. It's not
enough oxygen and nutrients
getting to the tissues, so you
need to revert the situation
as soon as possible by
increasing blood pressure.
So here is the
summary of what I just
told you. So let's say
in the case you have
accident or you have a
bleeding that will drop the
blood volume, you have a
drop in blood pressure.
So that can activate the
baroreceptor reflex to
try to reverse the
situation, increasing heart
rate, increase peripheral
So, one very typical
characteristic of
hypovolemic shock, you have
this huge vasoconstriction.
So, the patient will
develop this increase in
peripheral resistance in
order to try to increase
blood pressure. So,
this is very typical of
some bleeding situation.
The patient will definitely
develop vasoconstriction
and increase of
peripheral resistance
in order to try to
increase blood pressure.
Also, when we have a
decrease of blood pressure,
you will stimulate the
kidney to release renin and
activate the renin
-angiotensin system because we
need angiotensin too to
cause vasoconstriction.
So again, this is
something that is
highly asked in the
board exam. So here
I just put from the
USM and Lee book,
the hypovolemic shock,
when you have burn, huge
burn, dehydration, bleeding.
So the patient will
develop first this high
vasoconstriction,
increase of peripheral
resistance via the
baron receptor reflex.
So, during the
hypovolemic shock
you have decrease
of the preload,
that is the decrease
of venous return to the
heart. You will decrease
cardiac output, but you
see, you will increase
the systemic vascular
resistance because you
have this vasoconstriction
that's trying to
compensate the situation.
And the treatment, you
need to give volume.
If you give volume,
you increase stroke
volume, increase
cardiac output, and that
can lead to increasing
blood pressure.
So again, we have some
basic review questions. So
I list here the ones that
I think will help you to
to keep the main
information that
you need to know
about this lecture.
So, in the next slides,
I have all the answers.
So, if you have any
question, please
contact me and we
can discuss more. But
again, very
straightforward questions.
And when you have your
pharmacology lectures in
anti-hypertensive. I
hope you will remember
about the renin-angiotensin
system. So there is two
ways that we can interfere
in this system. We
can interfere this system
using ACE inhibitor.
So if we use ACE
inhibitor, we will not lead
angiotensin-2 to become
angiotensin-1 become
angiotensin 2, and also
we can use the ARBs, our
drugs that block the
receptor for angiotensin 2.
So even though we can have
high levels of angiotensin 2,
the herbs here, they will not
let this peptide to
bind to its receptor.
So that's all for this lecture.
This is all the reference
have been used. Thank
you and if you have any
question here is my email.